Guide to the American Dance Festival Records, circa 1924-1985, bulk 1934-1977 ADF.015
American Dance Festival Archives
- Administration, circa 1924-1981
  - Connecticut College, circa 1940-1981, 0.83 Linear Feet (Box 8)
    Contains correspondence, memos, form letters, articles of incorporation, legal documents, schedules, administrative materials, budgets, drafts, newspaper clippings, brochures, publicity materials, programs, application forms, floor plans, lists of faculty, staff, and students, policy information, library information including lists of overdue library books, campus maps and information, course lists, security reports, Connecticut visitor information, and a 1972 proposal to establish a MFA in dance at Connecticut College. The documents portray ADF's working relationship with Connecticut College and New York University as host institutions. Materials refer to decades of policy decisions, organization, and administration actions.
  - Facilities and Central Services, 1947-1977, 0.42 Linear Feet (Box 8)
    Contains correspondence, memos, form letters, floor plans, facilities measurements, facilities information, material requests, request forms, room assignments, contracts and rental agreements, schedules, sign-up sheets, administrative materials, and brochures and publicity materials. Documents refer to the use and maintenance of the facilities and materials utilized by the American Dance Festival at Connecticut College. Facilities include performance and rehearsal space, dormitories, and common areas such as the swimming pool and library. Correspondence between Facility Services and ADF refers to festival organization and closing coordination and supplies needed. Other correspondence refers to rehearsal space, scheduling, fire drills, materials needed, and police scheduling.
  - Finance, 1947-1977, 7.5 Linear Feet (Box 9)
    Contains finance records of the organization except for records of Development and Fundraising individual donors and funding organizations. Documents reflect the functions of the Finance Office.
    Arranged first chronologically, then alphabetically within each year by the following subjects:
    Accounts
    Budgets
    Correspondence
    General Ledger
    Payroll
    Accounts are further divided into the following subjects:
    Community Projects
    Companies
    Donations and Grant Income
    Facilities
    Festival
    General and Administrative
    Insurance
    School
    Special Projects
    Students
    - 1947-1959 (Box 9)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 10)
    - 1966-1971 (Box 11)
    - 1972-1974 (Box 12)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 13)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 14)
  - Legal Documents, 1975-1977, 7 folders (Box 15)
    Contains IRS documents, correspondence, tax exemption information, press releases, articles of incorporations, bylaws, and nondiscrimination policy information. Materials refer to legal issues pertaining to the incorporation of ADF.
  - Personnel, 1948-1977, 0.05 Linear Feet (Box 16)
    Contains correspondence, resumes, administrative materials, form letters, newspaper clippings, grant applications, job advertisements, and faculty and staff listings related to employment of ADF administrative staff.
  - Press Office, 1948-1977, 2 Linear Feet (Box 15)
    Contains correspondence, press releases, drafts, form letters, invitation lists, mailing lists, schedules, budgets, telegrams, summary reports, advertising forms, publicity materials, radio interview information, advertisement materials, attendance lists, proofs, critics and press lists, critics' complementary tickets materials, newspaper clippings, reviews, advertisement distribution lists, and press conference materials. Materials relate publicity and press coverage for all aspects of ADF including school classes, festival performances, and community outreach programs. Materials also include coverage in publicity sources ranging from ADF press releases to newspaper reviews and radio interviews.
    - 1948-1970 (Box 15)
    - 1971-1977 (Box 17)
  - Publications Office, 1948-1977, 2 Linear Feet (Box 17)
    Contains correspondence, bulletins, publicity materials, drafts, proofs, costs sheets, program advertisement order forms, form letters, schedules, mailing lists, newspaper clippings, purchase orders, and receipts. Much of the materials refers to the annual school course guide, information booklets, ticket information, and the individual program playbills. These materials include schedules, course listings, artist information, lists of advertisers, and advertisement proofs.
    - 1948-1963 (Box 17)
    - 1964-1977 (Box 18)
  - Social Gatherings and Parties, 1950-1977, 17 folders (Box 19)
    Contains guest lists, faculty and student listings, correspondence, invitations, form letters, schedules, hostess lists, and food and supplies lists. Materials refer to the variety of brunches, dinners, receptions, and social gatherings that occurred during the American Dance Festival, including materials referring to the 25th Anniversary Opening Gala and Reception and the 1977 reception to honor Sir Peter Ramsbotham, Lady Ramsbotham, and the London Contemporary Dance theater Company.
  - New Site Search, 1976-1977 (Box 19)
    In 1976, Connecticut College president Oakes Ames claimed that hosting ADF cost the college too much money and opted to charge the festival an additional yearly fee to cover operating costs. Festival Director Charles Reinhart, working with Administrative Directors Lisa Booth and Mary Jane Ingram, began considering a move to a different location. In August 1976, the Connecticut Commission on the Arts set up an inquiry into the future of ADF in Connecticut. The panel made two recommendations: that ADF should remain at Connecticut College for the 1977 season, and that both parties should undertake a joint study into the relationship between the festival and the college.
    ADF decided to terminate its relationship with Connecticut College and issued a press release in November 1976 stating their intention to move, resulting in phone calls and written requests from prospective sites. ADF compiled an initial list of possible locations. Meanwhile, the Connecticut Commission on the Arts study continued, with those involved knowing that ADF was leaving. In addition to financial disputes, the study highlighted other problems, mainly a perceived change in Connecticut College's attitude towards the festival: study participants felt that the college viewed ADF as a business proposition rather than an artistic entity. Also mentioned was a shortage of adequate facilities at Connecticut College.
    Throughout the study, ADF had been moving forward with plans to research potential locations. By August 1977 Reinhart, Booth, and Ingram had narrowed their choices and asked for proposals from 14 institutions. An advisory panel to help choose the new site was created. Unable to make a final selection, the panel decided to request more information from three front-runners: the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, and Duke University. After receiving the additional information, the panel reconvened to discuss their findings and ultimately chose Duke University.
    - Decision Process, circa 1976-1977, 11 folders (Box 19)
      Contains correspondence, press releases, meeting drafts, and notes explaining the events leading up to and the motivation behind the move, encompassing a time frame beginning in August 1976 with a Connecticut Commission on the Arts inquiry into a financial dispute between ADF and Connecticut College, and ending with work generated by an Advisory Panel assembled to choose the ADF's new location. Also included is a study of ADF's purpose and its relationship to Connecticut College and initial work regarding selecting a new site.
    - Potential Sites, circa 1976-1977, 11 folders (Box 19)
      Contains information and correspondence from over 40 universities, colleges, and arts organizations interested in hosting ADF. The 11 proposals from the most seriously considered sites are included, as well as additional requested information from the three final candidates.
      Arranged alphabetically.
- Performance, 1948-1977 and undated (Box 19)
  From 1948 to 1968, festival performances were held during the last part of the dance school's six-week course and were open to the public as well as the dance school community. For several years, the performances were held during the last week or extended weekend of the school. Gradually, performances began to be held during the last two or three weeks. Beginning in 1972, performances were given throughout the summer. In 1976 and 1977, ADF also held a public performance season in Newport, Rhode Island, in addition to the regular season in New London, Connecticut.
  - Commissions, 1954-1977, 9 folders (Box 19)
    Arranged chronologically and within each year alphabetically by company or artist name.
    1954 marked the first year that the School of the Dance commissioned choreography. The recipient was long-time ADF faculty member and noted choreographer, Jose Limon, and he created "The Traitor" for the summer season. Funds for Limon's work came from a surplus in the previous season's budget, but in subsequent years, ADF sought foundations and individuals to sponsor commissions. During the Connecticut period, commissioned artists included Jose Limon, Doris Humphrey, Erick Hawkins, Vivian Fine, Paul Draper, Lucas Hoving, Paul Taylor, Ruth Currier, and Rudy Perez.
    Contains proposals and correspondence commissioning artists, both dancers and musicians, to create works for performance during the ADF summer season.
  - Company Travel and Accommodations, 1952-1977, 0.3 Linear Feet (Box 19)
    Contains correspondence, administrative lists, dormitory floor plans, and itineraries concerning performing companies', orchestras', and musical accompanists' travel arrangements, housing, and meals.
  - Performance Contracts, 1957-1977, 0.3 Linear Feet (Box 19)
    Contains contracts and letters of agreement between ADF and performing companies and musicians and musical groups, including companies that were brought to ADF as a part of special projects, such as Music and Dance.
    Arranged in chronologically and divided into special project categories when applicable. Within each year and special project category, materials are arranged alphabetically by company or artist name.
  - Performers' Files, 1948-1977, 1.25 Linear Feet (Box 20)
    Contains letters to and from performers, schedules, company rosters, blank copies of contracts, and limited biographical materials relating to the company, solo and duet performers, or guest artists. Records often discuss plans for choreography, as well as logistics about scheduling, housing, production, performance, and publicity. Performers' Files include performers and musicians involved in special projects that were active during the 1970s, such as Music and Dance, Emerging Generation, and the Dance Touring Project.
    Arranged chronologically and within each year alphabetically by surname within company name.
  - Performance Office, 1948-1977, 0.25 Linear Feet (Box 21)
    Contains records that document the administrative side of coordinating performances, but not the decision-making processes of season programming (see Season Programming series), including information about mailings regarding the performance season, requests for performance season schedules (letters of interest), correspondence regarding contracting musicians and/or musical groups to accompany festival performances, correspondence with ADF-hired orchestra managers, such as Arnold Goldberg, and internal correspondence about the administration of the performance season. No official "Performance Office" existed during ADF's years at Connecticut College.
  - Production, 1948-1977 and undated, 1.25 Linear Feet (Box 21)
    Contains correspondence, schedules, lighting cues and plots, costume and set design notes and sketches, lists of orchestra personnel, and production notes. Occasionally includes materials regarding other events that took place in the theater which required technical assistance. Crew Correspondence documents the participation of individual crew members, such as the Technical Director, Stage Manager, and Lighting Designer. Other correspondence in this series covers requests for theater equipment from theater supply companies or dance companies, including correspondence in early years with Jean Rosenthal at Theater Production Service. Also includes correspondence and notes from artists, such as Doris Humphrey, Pauline Lawrence Limon (for Jose Limon), and Paul Taylor, about costume and set design or specific production needs for choreographic works. Costume files may include correspondence from the choreographer, measurements for specific dancers, and lists of materials used to construct costumes for various choreographic pieces. Set designs may also include correspondence from the choreographer, notes, and diagrams for set designs. Although light plots and cues do not exist for every year or for every piece performed, a fair number of diagrams are available in this series, and are labeled by choreographer or performing group if known.
    Arranged chronologically with subdivisions by subject: Crew Correspondence, Rehearsal Schedules, Costume Designs, and Music Permissions.
    - 1948-1970 (Box 21)
    - 1970-1977 (Box 22)
  - Program Materials, 1948-1977, 0.75 Linear Feet (Box 22)
    Contains lists of repertory to be performed in a given ADF season, correspondence from performers listing choreography to be performed, program notes, and rough drafts and proofs of programs. Includes program materials of most performances, formal and informal, that were used to create printed programs that accompanied performances. Final versions of programs are files in Printed Material in the Programs series. Playbills are filed in Playbills in the Printed Material series.
  - Season Programming, 1948-1977, 0.75 Linear Feet (Box 22)
    Contains letters of interest to and from potential performers, lists of the season's performers, correspondence, and administrative materials concerning planning the season as a whole. Also includes materials created by the Festival Committee (initially known as the Executive Council), a group that determined the season programming from 1948 to 1968.
    Arranged chronologically with categories, where materials exist: Letters of Interest, Festival Committee, and Performers unable to attend.
    - 1948-1960 (Box 22)
    - 1961-1977 (Box 23)
- Special Projects, 1947-1985 (Box 23)
  - ADF Repertory Company, 1972-1973 (Box 23)
    Contains materials that document the history of the 1972 American Dance Festival Repertory Company from its organization through its performance reviews.
    The American Dance Festival Repertory Company was formed in 1972, recreating several important, older works. From its conception, the company was organized with the intent to exist for only one season. ADF also produced a film with Ted Steeg Productions documenting the choreography performed. The ADF Repertory Company Advisory Committee members included Charles Reinhart, Martha Hill, Teddy Wiesner, Jeannette Roosevelt, and Walter Terry. Each member submitted a list of potential works to recreate and then together, the committee narrowed the list to five works: Martha Graham's El Penitente, Doris Humphrey's New Dance and With My Red Fires, Jose Limon's Emperor Jones, and Charles Weidman's Flickers. In addition, Rudy Perez was asked to create a new work to commemorate the achievements of the ADF.
    - Administration, 1972, 9 folders (Box 23)
      Contains Advisory committee materials, correspondence with dancers and choreographers, administrative materials, forms and form letters, and reviews and background materials on certain pieces.
    - Films, 1972-1973, 3 folders (Box 23)
      Contains a proposal for film, administrative materials, contracts, and correspondence.
  - Artists in the Schools, 1971-1977, 0.25 Linear Feet (Box 23)
    Contains organization materials, transcription, form letters, correspondence, workshop materials, and information packets pertaining to the Artists in the Schools program.
    ADF hosted the annual workshop for this program beginning in the summer of 1972. Charles Reinhart was National Coordinator of the program from 1972-1977.
  - Dance Advance, 1962-1968, 7 folders (Box 23)
    Consists of correspondence relating to performance, schedules of performance, and printed programs listing pieces, choreographers, and performers, at Dance Advance events.
    Dance Advance was a touring group of advanced students attending the summer session of the Connecticut College School of Dance. The group was instituted to acquaint a greater audience with modern dance and to provide students with performance and choreography opportunities. The students were expected to audition previously created pieces and to provide their own costumes and music. Dance Advance performed several dates each summer at many sites in New England, including colleges, camps, and local festivals. The group was also filmed by several New England television stations.
  - Dance Critics Conference, 1970-1985, 13 folders (Box 23)
    Contains a list of participants, organizational materials, correspondence, form letters, application forms, conference reviews from participants, and film request materials. While a participants list contains the names of attendees from 1970-1985, other materials in this series end in 1977.
    The Dance Critics Conference grew out of a 1967 summer course in critical writing taught by Selma Jeanne Cohen. The Conference was a three week (initially four week) seminar that brought together a small group of practicing journalists from the United States and Canada to gain greater understanding of how to review and write about dance. Dance criticism techniques were expanded through methods such as a daily movement class, ADF program attendance, ADF class visitation, dance film observation, and active critique sessions with respected dance critics. In these sessions, participants discussed topics such as writing style and problems relating to dance and dance review in the critics' home communities, completed writing assignments including reviews, and discussed one another's reviews.
  - Dance Touring Program, 1976, 1 folders (Box 23)
    Consists of a schedule for the 1976-1977 Artists-In-Schools Dance Component Summer Workshop comprised of the Dance Touring Program Coordinator's Workshop and the June 25-July 1, 1976 American Dance Festival at the New London campus of Connecticut College. More information about the ADF's involvement in the Dance Touring Program, a National Endowment for the Arts-sponsored program, can be found in the Administration series, under the Foundations and Funding Organizations sub series.
  - Dance/Television Workshop, 1973-1977, 0.5 Linear Feet (Box 25)
    Contains correspondence, letters of interest, applications, publicity, administrative materials, and participant evaluations pertaining to workshops held at ADF for television professionals.
    - Applications, 1973-1977, 9 folders (Box 24)
  - Emerging Generation, 1974, 4 folders (Box 25)
    Contains correspondence, personal notation, form letters, and a press release regarding the 1974 Emerging Generation program designed to highlight up-and-coming choreographers and their companies, including Trisha Brown and Group, Laura Dean and Dance Company, Nora Guthrie and Ted Rotante, the Multigravitational Experiment Group, Sara and Jerry Pearson, and Pilobolus Dance Theatre.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Exhibits, 1949-1973, 10 folders (Box 25)
    Contains correspondence, form letters, administrative materials, and reviews regarding exhibits held at, or circulated by, the American Dance Festival, including traveling exhibits in the 1960s of slides and photographs designed to cultivate interest in the School of Dance.
  - Film and Notation Project, 1954-1972, 0.5 Linear Feet (Box 25)
    Contains correspondence, administration papers, form letters, Labanotation notes, a notated musical score, contract information, newsletters, magazine and newspaper clippings, advertisements, and reviews.
    The Film Notation project was an effort to preserve contemporary dances on film and in notation. Films were made under the direction of Helen Priest Rogers. Lucy Venable, President of the Dance Notation Bureau, directed the notation. Initial films were silent, but beginning in 1962, some films were made with sound. After 1965, all of films were made with sound. Many works were filmed and notated including those of Doris Humphrey, Jose Limon, Pauline Koner, Merce Cunningham, Paul Taylor, Alwin Nikolais, Ruth Currier, Helen Tamiris, and Charles Weidman.
  - Film Series, 1957-1974, 13 folders (Box 25)
    Consists of correspondence, promotional materials, brochures, film lists, press releases, administrative materials, rental requests, and ordering information, much of it referring to dance films that were available for rental, purchase, or loan from various companies and institutions. Also included are correspondence and film lists referring to films viewed either individually or as part of a semi-annual film series at the School of Dance under the auspices of Selma Jeanne Cohen.
  - Lecture Demonstrations and Panels, 1948-1974, 23 folders (Box 25)
    Series contains schedules, dance step instructions, lecture notes, correspondence, form letters, registration sheets, newspaper clippings, and programs relating to a variety of lectures and demonstrations, including a 1953 Festival appearance by Virginia Tanner and members of the Children's Dance Theatre of Brigham Young University, a 1964 demonstration of Labanotation in Creative Dance Teaching by students of Nadia Chilkovsky of the Philadelphia Dance Academy, a 1965 lecture-demonstration on Classical Japanese Dance by Shozo Sato, a 1969 critics conference that laid the foundation for the 1970 Dance Critics Conference, and lectures for 1970s "Horizons in Dance" courses.
  - Little Lecture Series, 1951-1970, 16 folders (Box 26)
    Contains correspondence, form letters, publicity materials, administration materials, tickets, reviews, newspaper and magazine clippings, course information, and lecture notes referring to a lecture series begun in 1951. Included is correspondence with potential lecturers (Aaron Copeland and William Schuman, for example) as well as those who did lecture including Walter Terry, Martha Graham, Jose Limon, Doris Humphrey, and Agnes de Mille. In 1956, the lecture series served as a portion of the Backgrounds and Aesthetics of Dance lecture-discussion course directed by George Beiswanger. In 1959 the series name was changed to the Little Concert-Lecture Series.
  - Mini-ADFs, 1976-1977, 16 folders (Box 26)
    Contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, form letters, postcards, tourism materials, rental forms, budget sheets, press releases, a 1976 prospectus on the benefits of Newport, RI, schedules, real estate agency contact information, and permits referring to the ADF's stay in Newport during 1976 and 1977. Also contains letters and in house documents related to the search for a new site for the festival.
    In 1976, Mayor Humphrey J. Donnelly of Rhode Island invited the festival to Newport. After holding its 1976 season of classes and performances in New London, ADF also gave a week of performances in Newport. In addition, the festival also held community classes and workshops.
  - Music and Dance (MAD), 1974-1977, 5 folders (Box 26)
    Contains schedules, newspaper articles, correspondence, contracts, administration materials, press releases, and a NEA grant application regarding Project: Music and Dance.